Guide to the Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action Collection BCMS.0043
Brooklyn Collection
Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action Collection
1957-2012
1965-1972
Brooklyn Collection
Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action.
Moshette, Sydney, Jr.
BCMS.0043
4.59 Linear feet in 7 document boxes, 1 oversize box
Documents relating to Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action, a social action organization operating in the Bedford-Stuyvesant community from 1963-1978. The organization focused on community revitalization through programs targeted at underprivileged youth.
Historical Note
Youth in Action, Inc. (YIA) was formed in 1963 when the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council received a grant to develop a youth services program in the Bedford-Stuyvesant community. The Council decided to create YIA as its own organization rather than running it under the umbrella of the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council. Early staff members drew inspiration from existing social action organizations such as Mobilization for Youth and Harlem Youth Opportunities (HARYOU), spending the first months of operation researching and reporting on the needs of the Bedford-Stuyvesant community.
The passing of the Economic Opportunities Act of 1964 allowed YIA continued funding and led to the development of programs such as Training for Young Unwed Mothers, Youth Leadership Training Institute, Educational Remediation, and Cultural Arts. The increased funds allowed the organization to expand quickly, with many of their new hires coming from the community.
In July 1966 employees protested the organization, accusing them of under-representing the Puerto Rican population of Bedford-Stuyvesant and demanded that the organization's programs take more direct action in the community. The protests were followed by employee resignations, including Executive Director Dorothy Orr. Orr was replaced by Walter Pinkston, who served as Executive Director until his termination in September 1969.
A 1966 amendment to the Economic Opportunities Act called for greater involvement of community members in the social action organizations that represented them. YIA responded by converting to the Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action Community Corporation. Over 500 community members voted unanimously for the conversion which was approved by the Council Against Poverty in March 1967. A new Board of Directors was elected by community members to represent Bedford-Stuyvesant's five sub-districts.
By 1967 YIA had a staff of 300 with an additional 1,300 training aids and received $6.4 million dollars for the 1967-1968 fiscal year. The funds were directed to a variety of programs including job training, legal services and the popular Young Mothers program. The organization's rapid expansion allowed for increased services but also accusations of fund mismanagement, administrative oversight and cronyism. Years of factionalism and political in-fighting further destabilized the organization's mission, resulting in the June 1976 suspension of the Board of Directors. The organization was disbanded by the Koch administration in 1978.
Scope and Contents
The first series of this collection consists of documents relating to the founding and daily operations of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action organization. These documents make up the bulk of the collection and include administrative papers, meeting minutes, and promotional materials. Also included are studies and reports written by Youth in Action and outside organizations to assess community needs and concerns.
The second series includes documents relating to other community organizations operating simultaneously or prior to Youth in Action. These organizations served as models, partners and rivals to Youth in Action.
The third and smallest series includes personal documents from Sydney Moshette Jr. a probation officer and original Youth in Action board member. These include various papers written and collected during his time at New York University Graduate School of Public Administration and Social Service. Also included are miscellaneous notes and correspondence.
Access
This collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at Brooklyn Public Library's Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
This collection was compiled by Dr. Don Watkins and Sydney Moshette Jr. and gifted to David Rosner. Mr. Roser passed the collection to Mike Woodsworth who donated it to the Brooklyn Collection on July 12, 2016.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Contains seven subseries arranged by topic. Folders under each subseries are grouped by topic and arranged chronologically.
Series II: Contains nine subseries arranged alphabetically by organization. Folders under each subseries are grouped by topic and arranged chronologically.
Series III: Contains three folders arranged by topic.
Oversize folders are arranged by subseries in Box 8.
Related Archival Materials note
Brooklyn Archival Files – Bedford-Stuyvesant
Economic Development Programs in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, New York, under the Special Impact Program: Report to the Congress. U.S. General Accounting Office, 1973
Purnell, Brian. A movement grows in Brooklyn: the Brooklyn chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and the northern civil rights movement during the early 1960's. Ann Arbor, MI: UMI 2006
Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning, Brooklyn Public Library – Brooklyn Collection.
Rioghan Kirchner Civil Rights in Brooklyn Collection, Brooklyn Collection, Brooklyn Public Library.
Woodsworth, Michael. Battle for Bed-Stuy, The Long War on Poverty in New York City. Harvard University Press, 2016.
Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Poverty--United States; Social action--United States--History--20th century
- Series I: Youth in Action
  - Subseries I: Administrative
    - Docket for Meeting on Pilot Project, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Youth in Action Proposal, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Youth in Action Plan, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - By-Laws and Constitution, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - By-Laws and Constitution, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Conversion to Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action Community Corporation, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Conversion to Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action Community Corporation, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Youth in Action Information Packets, circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Finance and Budget, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Personnel, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Personnel, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Elections, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Youth in Action Evaluations, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Youth in Action Evaluations, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Administrative Oversize, circa 1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II: Board of Directors and Committees
    - Minutes and Papers, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Minutes and Papers, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Minutes and Papers, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Minutes and Papers, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Minutes and Papers, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Minutes and Papers, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Minutes and Papers, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ad-Hoc Council for Crime Prevention and Control, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Achievement and Award Committee, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Conference Planning, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Constitution and By-Law Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Decentralization Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Education Committee, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Election Committee, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Joint Committees, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Nominating Committee, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Subseries III: Community Studies and Reports
    - Studies and Surveys Conducted by Youth in Action, circa 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Studies and Surveys Conducted by Other Organizations, 1930-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Studies and Surveys Conducted by Other Organizations, circa 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Studies and Surveys Conducted by Other Organizations, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Studies and Surveys Conducted by Other Organizations, 1968-1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Community Studies and Surveys (oversize), circa 1965 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Subseries IV: Programs
    - General, circa 1966-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Headstart, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - Homework Study, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Negro and Puerto Rican Heritage, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Proposals, 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Young Mothers, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Programs (oversize), Box 8, circa 1967 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Subseries V: Press and Promotional
    - Clippings, 1963-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Fliers, circa 1965-1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Newsletters: The Arrow, 1966 (Aug.) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Newsletters: Youth in Action Newsletters, 1966, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Newsletters: Manpower Review, 1972 (April-Aug.) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Newsletters: Youth in Action Staff Newsletter (cover only), 1965 (Dec.) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Newsletters (oversize), 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Press Releases, 1965-1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Testimony and Position Papers, 1966-1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Press and Promotional (oversize), circa 1967-2013 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries VI: Correspondence
    - Memorandums and Correspondence, 1965-1976, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Notes and Correspondence (re: YIA collection transfer), 1996-2004 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Suberies VII: Photographs
    - Photographs, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series II: Other Organizations
  - Subseries I: Associated Community Teams
    - Calendar (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II: Bedford-Stuyvesant Council on Crime Control and Prevention
    - Constitution, circa 1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III: Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corp.
    - Newsletters, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IV: Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council
    - By-Laws and Constitution, circa 1962 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Personnel, circa 1965 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council History, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Minutes and Papers, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Fliers, circa 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Newsletter: Brooklyn Coordinating Council News Briefs, 1975 (July/Aug.) (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Statements and Position Papers, 1963-1967 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (oversize), 1962-1967 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Subseries V: City Commission on Human Rights
    - Fliers (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subseries VI: Harlem Youth Opportunities (HARYOU)
    - Press and Promotional, 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Subseries VII: Mobilization for Youth, Folder 67: Organization and Program Evaluations, circa 1962-1966 Folder 68: Training Seminar Agenda, 1962 Folder 69: Program Proposal, 1962 Folder 70: Newsletter: Mobilization for Youth News Bulletin, 1965 (Summer) Folder 71: Newsletter: Mobilization for Youth News Bulletin, 1966 (Summer) Folder 72: Newsletter: Mobilization for Youth News Bulletin, 1966-1967 (Winter) Oversize Folder, Box 8: Mobilization for Youth, 1964-1967
    - Organization and Program Evaluations, circa 1962-1966 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Training Seminar Agenda, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Program Proposal, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Newsletter: Mobilization for Youth News Bulletin, 1965 (Summer) (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Newsletter: Mobilization for Youth News Bulletin, 1966 (Summer) (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Newsletter: Mobilization for Youth News Bulletin, 1966-1967 (Winter) (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Mobilization for Youth (oversize), 1964-1967 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Subseries VIII: National Black Caucus on Police
    - Seminar and Meeting Documents, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Subseries IX: Neighborhood Youth Corps.
    - Information Packet, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Series III: Sydney Moshette, Jr. Personal Papers
  - College Papers, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Notes, circa 1996 (Box 7, Folder 24)